Guide to the Tony Martin Papers, 1960-2018 MSS.190
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series I: Documentary and Graphic Material, 104831
  - Subseries B: Visual Compositions, Performances & Lectures, 104930
    - San Francisco Tape Music Center Retrospective: Works of 1963-66 - Victoria Theater, San Francisco, CA, 1988; 104943 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - New Year Ensemble - Williamsburg Art & Historical Center, Brooklyn, NY, 1999; 104942 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Retrospective for works performed in collaboration with composers of the San Francisco Tape Music Center, and more recent video projection piece - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, Los Angeles, CA, 2000; 104941 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - "Tools for the Spirit": A talk on the artist's work and influences - New York Studio School of Drawing, Painting and Sculture, New York, NY, 2001; 104940 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Over Under Across, video projection installation - Eyebeam, Beta Launch N.Y.C., New York, NY, 2002; 104939 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Visual Poetry in Light in Time, three works for projection - Sideshow Gallery, Brooklyn, NY, 2003; 104938 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Light Marks Converse for computer and video projection; Sidewinder with Morton Subotnick liquid projection, painting in time - Cal Arts Theater at Disney Center, Los Angeles, CA, 2003; 104937 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Mode Records release Sidewinder with Morton Subotnick; March 2004, 104936 (Box 1, Folder 70, Case 190.0013)
    - Interpretation Series Concert - Merkin Hall, New York, NY, 2004; 104935 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Wow and Flutter - Compositions for light, with composers of the San Francisco Tape Music Center, 1963-67 - EMPAC at RPI, 2004; 104934 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Legendary Light Shows - Rotterdam Film Festival, Rotterdam, The Netherlands, 2006; 104933 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Anthony Martin, Visual Composer - Songlines Series, Center for Contemporary Music, Mills College, Oakland, CA, 2006; 104932 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Miscellaneous slides depicting light projection compositions, 1965-1971; 104931 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Spectral Created Sound (photographs), 156887 (Box 1, Folder 75.5)
  - Subseries C: Interactive Sculptures, 104923
    Consists mostly of announcements and photographs pertaining to Tony Martin's interactive sculptures. Abundant sketches and notes (including schematics) relating to material in Subseries C may be found in Subseries D, under "Interactive Sculptures," "New Media Works…" and the individual names of the installations.
    - Interaction Room (or Game Room) (20 x 20 x 10 room containing light and projection installation activated by viewers using game principles) - Howard Wise Gallery, New York, NY ***see also*** Oversize, 1968; 104929 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Column - Howard Wise Gallery, New York, NY, 1969; 104928 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Door - Howard Wise Gallery, New York, NY, 1969; 104927 (Box 1, Folder 78)
      General
      "Door" is in the permanent collection of the Butler Institute of American Art, Youngstown, OH
    - The Well - Everson Museum, permanent collection, Syracuse, NY, 1969; 104926 (Box 1, Folder 79)
      "The Well" is in the permanent collection of the Everson Museum, Syracuse, NY
    - You, Me, We - Howard Wise Gallery, New York, NY, 1969; 104925 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Word Wall - Longridge Plaza, permanent collection, Rochester, NY, 1975; 104924 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Subseries D: Sketches, Notes & Miscellaneous, 104908
    Contains rich material relating to Subseries C: Interactive Sculptures, including handwritten notes, sketches and schematics of electronic circuits. Other material includes contact sheets as well as press clippings pertaining to Tony Martin's works. Subseries D is arranged alphabetically.
    - Address book / Appointment book / Notebook, [n.d.]; 104922 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Biography & Chronology of New Media Works, 2006; 104921 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Circuitry (with Pauline Oliveros), 1967+2004, [n.d.]; 104920 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Door - Sketches and schematics of electronic circuits, 1968; 104919 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Interactive Sculptures, including "Column" and "The Well", 1968; 104918 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - New Media Works including "Climate Sculpture," "Nodes," and "Xytopy", 1967-1972; 104917 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Photograph of Tony Martin, Sal Martirano, William Wegman, ca. 1969; 104916 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Press - miscellaneous, [n.d.]; 104915 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Schematics of electronic circuits for Carl Countryman, Game Room, E.A.T., 1966-1971; 104914 (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Score Drawings - "storyboard-composition", ca. 1970s; 104913 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Sequences, ca. 1970s; 104912 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Sketches, Drawings for Pieces ***see also*** Oversize, ca. 1970s; 104911 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Theater Sculpture For Watchers, Walkers, Touchers (a 140 foot long interactive polysensory course in an octagonal room) - San Francisco Museum of Art, CA, 1963; 104910 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Word Wall - Longridge Plaza, permanent collection, Rochester, NY, 1974; 104909 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Subseries E: Correspondence, 104832
    Consists mainly of Tony Martin's letter and e-mail correspondence with notable artists and art organizations. Subseries E is arranged alphabetically by two main groups, individuals and institutions.
    - Individuals - Ashton, Dore, 1992-1998; 104907 (Box 1, Folder 96)
    - Individuals - Bermant, David W., 1995; 104906 (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - Individuals - Bly, Carol, 1994; 104905 (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - Individuals - Bly, Robert, 104904 (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - Individuals - Caws, Mary Ann, 1996; 104903 (Box 1, Folder 100)
    - Individuals - Chadabe, Joel, 1996; 104902 (Box 1, Folder 101)
    - Individuals - Conte, Richard, 1990; 104901 (Box 1, Folder 102)
    - Individuals - Dowling, Jack, 104900 (Box 1, Folder 103)
    - Individuals - Friedman, Martin, 2002; 104899 (Box 1, Folder 104)
    - Individuals - Gerz, Jochen, 2004; 104898 (Box 1, Folder 105)
    - Individuals - Harnhardt-Whitney, John, 104897 (Box 1, Folder 106)
    - Individuals - Jordan, Larry, 1991-1994; 104896 (Box 1, Folder 107)
    - Individuals - Kramarsky, Werner H., 1996; 104895 (Box 1, Folder 108)
    - Individuals - Marker, Helene, 104894 (Box 1, Folder 109)
    - Individuals - Moorman, Charlotte, 104893 (Box 1, Folder 110)
    - Individuals - Mulder, Jan, 1999; 104892 (Box 1, Folder 111)
    - Individuals - Ochs, Hunter, 2003; 104891 (Box 1, Folder 112)
    - Individuals - Oliveros, Pauline, 2000-2001; 104890 (Box 1, Folder 113)
    - Individuals - Paik, Nam June, 1980-2006; 104889 (Box 1, Folder 114)
    - Individuals - Pickover, Clifford A., 104888 (Box 1, Folder 115)
    - Individuals - Popper, Frank, 1994-1995; 104887 (Box 1, Folder 116)
    - Individuals - Redmond, Catherine, 1994; 104886 (Box 1, Folder 117)
    - Individuals - Reiser, Beverly, 1991; 104885 (Box 1, Folder 118)
    - Individuals - Sender, Ramon, 1981; 104884 (Box 1, Folder 119)
    - Individuals - Subotnick, Joan La Barbara, 104883 (Box 1, Folder 120)
    - Individuals - Tenney, James, 2005; 104882 (Box 1, Folder 121)
    - Individuals - Tudor, David, 1996; 104881 (Box 1, Folder 122)
    - Individuals - Vitiello, Stephen, 2005; 104880 (Box 1, Folder 123)
    - Individuals - Westermann, Joanna Beall, 104879 (Box 1, Folder 124)
    - Individuals - Miscellaneous, 104878 (Box 1, Folder 125)
    - Institutions - American Poetry Review, 2005; 104877 (Box 1, Folder 126)
    - Institutions - Art in America, 1994; 104876 (Box 1, Folder 127)
    - Institutions - The Art Students League of New York, 1994; 104875 (Box 1, Folder 128)
    - Institutions - Baltimore Film Forum, 1993; 104874 (Box 1, Folder 129)
    - Institutions - The Butler Institute of American Art, [n.d.]; 104873 (Box 1, Folder 130)
    - Institutions - Dia Art Foundation, 2005; 104872 (Box 1, Folder 131)
    - Institutions - Duke University, 1969; 104871 (Box 1, Folder 132)
    - Institutions - European American Music Distributors Corporation, 1993; 104870 (Box 1, Folder 133)
    - Institutions - Everson Museum, 2003; 104869 (Box 1, Folder 134)
    - Institutions - Eyebeam Atelier, 2000; 104868 (Box 1, Folder 135)
    - Institutions - The Franklin Institute, 1992; 104867 (Box 1, Folder 136)
    - Institutions - Guggenheim Museum SoHo, 1996; 104866 (Box 1, Folder 137)
    - Institutions - The Institute for Art and Urban Resources, Inc., 1982; 104865 (Box 1, Folder 138)
    - Institutions - Joseloff Gallery, 1996; 104864 (Box 1, Folder 139)
    - Institutions - Kingsborough Community College Art Gallery of the City University of New York, 1996; 104863 (Box 1, Folder 140)
    - Institutions - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 2000; 104862 (Box 1, Folder 141)
    - Institutions - Mills College, 1996-2004; 104861 (Box 1, Folder 142)
    - Institutions - Mt. Utsayantha Regional Arts League, 1995; 104860 (Box 1, Folder 143)
    - Institutions - Musee d'Art Moderne de la Ville de Paris, 1999; 104859 (Box 1, Folder 144)
    - Institutions - Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles, CA, 2004-2005; 104858 (Box 1, Folder 145)
    - Institutions - Museum of Modern Art, Brooklyn, NY, [n.d.]; 104857 (Box 1, Folder 146)
    - Institutions - National Council on the Arts, 1972; 104856 (Box 1, Folder 147)
    - Institutions - New Museum of Contemporary Art, Brooklyn, NY, 2001; 104855 (Box 1, Folder 148)
    - Institutions - The New York Times, 2001; 104854 (Box 1, Folder 149)
    - Institutions - Oregon College of Education, 1970; 104853 (Box 1, Folder 150)
    - Institutions - The Painting Center, New York, NY, 1998; 104852 (Box 1, Folder 151)
    - Institutions - Pilgrim Society, 1975; 104851 (Box 1, Folder 152)
    - Institutions - PSC-CUNY Research Award Program, 1993; 104850 (Box 1, Folder 153)
    - Institutions - Rennaissance Center, Detroit, MI, 1976; 104849 (Box 1, Folder 154)
    - Institutions - San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, [n.d.]; 104848 (Box 1, Folder 155)
    - Institutions - Santa Barbara Museum of Art, 1994; 104847 (Box 1, Folder 156)
    - Institutions - Scott Alan Fine Arts Gallery, 1992; 104846 (Box 1, Folder 157)
    - Institutions - Seoul Film Festival, 2005; 104845 (Box 1, Folder 158)
    - Institutions - Simon Gallery, 1999; 104844 (Box 1, Folder 159)
    - Institutions - Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1994; 104843 (Box 1, Folder 160)
    - Institutions - Stedelijk Museum Amsterdam, 1998; 104842 (Box 1, Folder 161)
    - Institutions - Studio 18 Gallery, 2004; 104841 (Box 1, Folder 162)
    - Institutions - Tibor de Nagy Gallery, [n.d.]; 104840 (Box 1, Folder 163)
    - Institutions - The University of Iowa, Center for the New Performing Arts, 1970; 104839 (Box 1, Folder 164)
    - Institutions - Walter Wickiser Gallery, 1994; 104838 (Box 1, Folder 165)
    - Institutions - Washburn Gallery, 1996; 104837 (Box 1, Folder 166)
    - Institutions - Westdeutscher Rundfunk WDR, 2003-2004; 104836 (Box 1, Folder 167)
    - Institutions - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1967-1993; 104835 (Box 1, Folder 168)
    - Institutions - The Woody Guthrie Film Project, 2005; 104834 (Box 1, Folder 169)
    - Institutions - Ylem, 1992; 104833 (Box 1, Folder 170)
- Series II: Book Collection, 104830; Martin, Tony, 1937-
  Scope and Content note
  The book collection is housed in the Fales Library. The books have been catalogued in Bobcat. A keyword or related name search with the name "Tony Martin" will retrieve the records - see "Separated Materials" for a list of the removed books.
  Wise, Howard
- Series III: Video Recordings and Motion Picture Film, 104805
  Conditions Governing Access
  There may not be access copies available for all audiovisual material. Please contact a Fales archivist.
  - Subseries A: Video Recordings, 104813
    Consists of screen projections from Tony Martin's visual compositions, recordings of performances and an interview.
    Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 to request item by using the access DVD ID number.
    - "Bridge", 1980; ID: 190.0001; 104828 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0001, Case 190.0023)
      General note
      Original format:
      Duration: unknown
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0023.
    - "Flash" performance - Katonah Museum of Art, February 7, 1981; ID: 190.0002; 104827 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0002, Case 190.0026)
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0026.
    - WHO YOU ARE LOOKING FOR IS WHO IS LOOKING; - Audio: STEREO, February 18, 1992; ID: 190.0003; 104826 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0003, Case 190.0030)
      Original format: VHS
      Duration: 6 minutes
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0030.
    - Tape Music Center Concert Retrospective in San Francisco, undated; ID: 190.0004; 104825 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0004, Case 190.0032)
      Duration: 102 minutes
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0032.
    - 2, undated; ID: 190.0005; 104824 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0005, Case 190.0034)
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0034.
    - FIVE STANZAS, 2003; ID: 190.0006; 104823 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0006, Case 190.0036)
      Original format: Betacam SP Mega
      Duration: 7 minutes
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0036.
    - Over Under Across; Finished at Standby, January 2003; ID: 190.0007; 104822 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0007, Case 190.0038)
      Original format: Betacam SP
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0038.
    - FIVE STANZAS - silent 5 minutes -, c.1970, 2003; ID: 190.0008; 104821 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0008, Case 190.0040)
      Original format: DVD
      Duration: 5 minutes
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0040.
    - Tony Martin interview; Mode Records re: Brian Brandt - N.Y.C., January 28, 2004; ID: 190.0009; 104820 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0009, Case 190.0043)
      Duration: 37 minutes
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0043.
    - sunloom - 6 minutes silent, 2005; ID: 190.0010; 104819 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0010, Case 190.0049)
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0049.
    - Conversing; Ear to the Ground; In the Wake of Edges, 2005; ID:190.0011; 104818 (Box 3, Media ID:190.0011, Case 190.0046)
      Duration: 13 minutes
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0046.
    - Wow & Flutter: The San Francisco Tape Music Center 1961 - now, undated; ID: 190.0012; 104817 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0012, Case 190.0051)
      Duration: 76 minutes
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0012.
    - WHO YOU ARE LOOKING FOR IS WHO IS LOOKING; - Audio: STEREO, February 18, 1992; ID: 190.0014; 104815 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0014)
      Original format: 1"
      Duration: [unknown]
    - Light Marks Converse; ~one hour: 4 takes; 2003, 2004, January 27, 2004; ID: 190.0015; 104814 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0015, Case 190.0060)
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0060.
      Original format: DVCam
      Duration: 60 minutes
    - Game Room at Howard Wise Gallery, 1968; ID: 190.0027; 154060 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0027, Case 190.0062)
      Duration: 2 minutes
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD #190.0062.
    - Tony Martin Interview, February 27, 2004; ID: 190.0068; 154061 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0068, Case 190.0065)
      Orginal format: VHS
      Duration: 120 minutes
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD #190.0065.
    - "Play I"-Tony Martin, undated; ID: 190.0066; 154062 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0066, Case 190.0054)
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0054.
      Duration: 3 minutes
    - Tony Martin-Improvisations, October 13, 2004; ID: 190.0067; 154063 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0067, Case 190.0057)
      Orignal format: DVD
      Duration: 27 minutes
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0057.
    - Tony Martin Interview with Julie Martin, February 7, 2007; ID: 190.0069; 154064 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0069, Case 190.0072)
      Duration: 80 minutes
      Access DVD available. Please request access DVD # 190.0072.
    - SF Tape Music Center Revisited, Undated; ID: 190.0005; 155639 (Box 3, Media ID: 190.0005)
      General Note
      Duration: 80 mintues
  - Subseries B: Motion Picture Film, 104806
    Scope and Contents Note
    Consists of Tony Martin's visual compositions, mostly in collaboration with other artists, along with paper documentation regarding some of the works. Paper documents stored within film cans have been removed, foldered, and given the same ID number as the corresponding film element but with a letter B at end of ID number. (Ex. Film: 190.0001A, Folder 190.0001B.)
    Film materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
    - Tarot, 1964-1965; 104811 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0016A)
      Original format: 16mm
    - Tarot - Artist's Descriptive Notes, Undated; 154123 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0016B)
    - Desert Ambulance; silent; 1963, 104810 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0017)
    - Room - '63-64, 1963-1964; 104809 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0018)
    - "Play 4" Film I; all illumination for Morton Subotnick, 1967; 104808 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0019A)
    - "Play 4" Film I - Artist's Descriptive Notes, Undated; 154124 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0019B)
    - "Play 4" Film II; all illumination for Morton Subotnick, 1967; 104807 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0020A)
    - "Play 4" Film II - Artist's Descriptive Notes, Undated; 154125 (Box 4, Folder ID 190.0020B)
- Series IV: Objects, 104803
  - Electronic Circuitry for regulating intensity and off/on of light apparatus using frequency discrete photo cells, applied in "The Well" and "Light Pendulum", 104804 (Box 5)
    Box contains folder with description of object written by Tony Martin.
- OVERSIZE: Series I: Documentary and Graphic Material, 104789
  Contains oversize documentary and graphic material. Some entries are cross-listed with entries in Series I.
  - Subseries A: Exhibitions, 104800
    - Galaxy - James Madison University, Sawhill Gallery, Harrisburg, VA ***see also*** Series I, Subseries A, Box I, Folder 40, 2005; 104802 (Box 2, Folder 171)
    - The Inaugural Show - The Painting Center, New York, NY, [n.d.]; 104801 (Box 2, Folder 172)
  - Subseries B: Visual Compositions, Performances & Lectures, 104795
    - Original multi-projector light shows for groups including: The Jefferson Airplane, The Great Society, and more - Bill Graham's Fillmore West, San Francisco, CA, 1965-1967; 104799 (Box 2, Folder 173)
    - Silver Apples of the Moon (Morton Subotnick), c1967; 104798 (Box 2, Folder 174)
    - Vector Image Wall and works on paper: Continuously changing electronic drawing (electronic system and video projection) - Institute for Art & Urban Resources, P.S. 1, Long Island City, NY ***see also*** Series I, Subseries C, Box 1, Folder 62, 1980; 104797 (Box 2, Folder 175)
    - San Francisco Tape Music Center Retrospective: Works of 1963-66 - Victoria Theater, San Francisco, CA, 1988; 104796 (Box 2, Folder 176)
  - Subseries C: Interactive Sculptures, 104792
    - Interaction Room (or Game Room) (20 x 20 x 10 room containing light and projection installation activated by viewers using game principles) - Howard Wise Gallery, New York, NY ***see also*** Series I, Subseries C, Box 1, Folder 76, 1968; 104794 (Box 2, Folder 177)
    - Press: San Francisco Bay Guardian, 1996; 104793 (Box 2, Folder 178)
  - Subseries D: Sketches, Notes & Miscellaneous, 104790
    - Sketches, Drawings for Pieces ***see also*** Series I, Subseries D, Box 1, Folder 93, [n.d.]; 104791 (Box 2, Folder 179)